section 2 chapter 7.
Winston had woken up with his eyes full of tears. Julia rolled sleepily against
him, murmuring something that might have been 'What's the matter?'
'I dreamed he began, and stopped short.
It was too complex to be put into words.
There was the dream itself, and there was a memory connected with it that had
swung into his mind in the few seconds after waking.
He lay back with his eyes shut, still sodden in the atmosphere of the dream.
It was a vast, luminous dream in which his whole life seemed to stretch out
before him like a landscape on a summer evening after rain.
It had all occurred inside the glass paperweight, but the surface of the glass
was the dome of the sky, and inside the dome everything was flooded with clear
soft light in which one could see into interminable distances.
The dream had also been comprehended by— —indeed, in some sense it had consisted in—
—a gesture of the arm made by his mother, and made again 30 years later by the
Jewish woman he had seen on the news film, trying to shelter the small boy
from the bullets, before the helicopter blew them both to pieces.
'Do you know,' he said, 'that until this moment I believed I had murdered my mother?'
'Why did you murder her?' said Julia, almost asleep.
'I didn't murder her. Not physically.'
In the dream he had remembered his last glimpse of his mother, and within a few
moments of waking the cluster of small events surrounding it had all come back.
It was a memory that he must have deliberately pushed out of his consciousness over many years.
He was not certain of the date, but he could not have been less than 10 years
old, possibly 12 when it had happened.
His father had disappeared sometime earlier; how much earlier, he could not remember.
He remembered better the rackety, uneasy circumstances of the time:
the periodical panics about Air Raids and the sheltering in Tube stations, the
piles of rubble everywhere, the unintelligible proclamations posted at
street corners, the gangs of youths in shirts all the same color the enormous
cues outside the bakeries, the intermittent machine gun fire in the distance—
—above all, the fact that there was never enough to eat.
He remembered long afternoons spent with other boys in scrounging round dustbins
and rubbish heaps, picking out the ribs of cabbage leaves, potato peelings,
sometimes even scraps of stale bread crust from which they carefully scraped away the cinders;
and also in waiting for the passing of trucks which traveled over a certain
route and were known to carry cattle feed, and which, when they jolted over the bad
patches in the road, sometimes spilled a few fragments of oil cake
When his father disappeared, his mother did not show any surprise or any violent
grief, but the sudden change came over her.
She seemed to have become completely spiritless.
It was evident even to Winston that she was waiting for something that she knew must happen.
She did everything that was needed— —cooked, washed, mended, made the bed, swept
the floor, dusted the mantelpiece— —always very slowly and with a curious
lack of superfluous motion, like an artist's sleigh figure moving of its own accord
a large shapely body seemed to relapse naturally into stillness.
For hours at a time she would sit almost immobile on the bed, nursing his young
sister, a tiny, ailing, very silent child of two or three, with a face made Simeon by thinness.
Very occasionally she would take Winston in her arms and press him against her
for a long time without saying anything.
He was aware, in spite of his youthfulness and selfishness, that this
was somehow connected with the never mentioned thing that was about to happen.
He remembered the room where they lived, a dark, close- smelling room that seemed
half-filled by a bed with a white counterpane.
There was a gas ring in the fender, and a shelf where food was kept, and on the
landing outside there was a brown earthenware sink, common to several rooms.
He remembered his mother's statuesque body bending over the gas ring to stir
at something in a saucepan.
Above all he remembered his continuous hunger, and the fierce sordered battles at meal times
He would ask his mother naggingly, over and over again, why there was not more
food, he would shout and storm at her (he even remembered the tones of his voice,
which was beginning to break prematurely and sometimes boomed in a peculiar way),
or he would attempt a sniveling note of pathos in his efforts to get more than his share.
His mother was quite ready to give him more than his share. She took it for
granted that he, 'the boy', should have the biggest portion; but however much she
gave him he invariably demanded more.
At every meal she would beseech him not to be selfish and to remember that his
little sister was sick and also needed food, but it was no use.
He would cry out with rage when she stopped laggling he would try to wrench
the saucepan and spoon out of her hands, he would grab bits from his sister's plate.
He knew that he was starving the other two, but he could not help it; he even
felt that he had a right to do it.
The Glamorous hunger in his belly seemed to justify him.
Between meals, if his mother did not stand guard, he was constantly pilfering
at the wretched store of food on the shelf.
One day a chocolate ration was issued.
There had been no such issue for weeks or months past.
He remembered quite clearly that precious little morsel of chocolate.
It was a two ounce slab (they still talked about answers in those days)
between the three of them.
It was obvious that a door to be divided into three equal parts.
Suddenly, as though you were listening to somebody else, Winston heard himself
demanding in a loud booming voice that he should be given the whole piece.
His mother told him not to be greedy.
There was a long, nagging argument that went round and round, with shouts fines
tears, remonstrances, bargainings.
His tiny sister, clinging to her mother with both hands, exactly like a baby
monkey, sat looking over her shoulder at him with large, mournful eyes.
In the end his mother broke off three quarters of the chocolate and gave it to
Winston, giving the other quarter to his sister.
The little girl took hold of it and looked at it dully, perhaps not knowing what it was.
Winston stood watching her for a moment.
Then with the sudden swift spring he had snatched to the piece of chocolate out
of his sister's hand and was fleeing for the door.
'Winston, Winston!' his mother called after him. 'Come back! Give your sister back her
chocolate!'
He stopped, but did not come back.
His mother's anxious eyes were fixed on his face.
Even now he was thinking about the thing, he did not know what it was that was on
the point of happening.
His sister, conscious of having been robbed of something, had set up a feeble whale
His mother drew her arm around the child and pressed its face against her breast.
Something in the gesture told him that his sister was dying. He turned and fled
down the stairs, with the chocolate growing sticky in his hand.
He never saw his mother again.
After he had devoured the chocolate he felt somewhat ashamed of himself and
hung about in the streets for several hours, until hunger drove him home.
When he came back his mother had disappeared.
This was already becoming normal at that time.
Nothing was gone from the room except his mother and his sister. They had not
taken any clothes, not even his mother's overcoat.
To this day he did not know with any certainty that his mother was dead.
It was perfectly possible that she had merely been sent to a forced labor camp.
As for his sister, she might have been removed, like Winston himself, to one of
the colonies for homeless children
(Reclamation centers they were called)
which had grown up as a result of the civil war;
or she might have been sent to the labor camp along with his mother,
or simply left somewhere or other to die.
The dream was still vivid in his mind, especially the enveloping, protecting
gesture of the arm in which its whole meaning seemed to be contained.
His mind went back to another dream of two months ago.
Exactly as his mother had sat on the dingy white quilted bed, with the child
clinging to her, so she had sat in the sunken ship, far underneath him and
drowning deeper every minute, but still looking up at him through the darkening water.
He told Julia the story of his mother's disappearance.
Without opening her eyes she rolled over and settled herself into a more comfortable position.
'I expect you were a beastly little swine in those days,' she said indistinctly. 'All
children are swine.'
'Yes. But the real point of the story— From her breathing it was evident that
she was going off to sleep again.
He would have liked to continue talking about his mother.
He did not suppose, from what he could remember of her, that she had been an
unusual woman, still less an intelligent one; and yet she had possessed a kind of
nobility, a kind of purity, simply because the standards that she obeyed were private ones.
Her feelings were her own, and could not be altered from outside.
It would not have occurred to her that an action which is ineffectual thereby
becomes meaningless.
If you loved someone, you loved him, and when you had nothing else to give, you
still gave him love.
When the last of the chocolate was gone, his mother had clasped the child in her
arms. It was no use, it changed nothing, it did not produce more chocolate, it did
not avert the child's death or her own; but it seemed natural to her to do it.
The refugee woman in the boat had also covered the little boy with her arm,
which was no more use against the bullets than a sheet of paper.
The terrible thing that the Party had done was to persuade you that mere
impulses, mere feelings, were of no account, while at the same time robbing
you of all power over the material world.
When once you were in the grip of the Party, what you felt or did not feel, what
you did or refrained from doing, made literally no difference.
Whatever happened you vanished, and neither you nor your actions were ever
heard of again. You were lifted clean out of the stream of history.
And yet to the people of only two generations ago, this would not have
seemed all important because they were not attempting to alter history.
They were governed by private loyalties which they did not question.
What mattered were individual relationships, and a completely helpless
gesture and embrace, a tear, a word spoken to a dying man, could have value in itself.
The pearls had suddenly occurred to him, had remained in this condition.
They were not loyal to a party or a country or an idea, they were loyal to
one another.
For the first time in his life he did not despise the pros or think of them
merely as an inert force which would one day spring to life and regenerate the world.
The pearls had stayed human.
They had not become hardened inside. They had held on to the primitive emotions
which he himself had to relearn by conscious effort.
And in thinking this he remembered, without apparent relevance, how a few
weeks ago he had seen a severed hand lying on the pavement and had kicked it
into the gutter as though it had been a cabbage stalk
The pros are human beings,' he said aloud.
'We are not human.'
'Why not?' said Julia, who had woken up again.
He thought for a little while.
'Has it ever occurred to you,' he said, 'that the best thing for us to do would be
simply to walk out of here before it's too late, and never see each other again?'
'Yes, dear, it has occurred to me, several times. But I'm not going to do it, all the
same.'
'We've been lucky,' he said, 'but it can't last much longer.
You're young. You look normal and innocent. If you keep clear of people
like me, you might stay alive for another 50 years.'
'No. I've thought it all out. What you do, I'm going to do. And don't be too
down-hearted I'm rather good at staying alive.'
'We may be together for another six months— —a year— —there's no knowing.
At the end we're certain to be a part Do you realize how utterly alone we shall be?
When once they get hold of us there will be nothing, literally nothing, that either
of us can do for the other.
If I confess, they'll shoot you, and if I refuse to confess they'll shoot you just the same.
Nothing that I can do or say, or stop myself from saying, will put off your
death for as much as five minutes.
Neither of us will even know whether the other is alive or dead.
We shall be utterly without power of any kind.
The one thing that matters is that we shouldn't betray one another, although
even that can't make the slightest difference.'
'If you mean confessing,' she said, 'we shall do that, right enough. Everybody always
confesses. You can't help it. They torture you.'
'I don't mean confessing. Confession is not betrayal. What you say or do doesn't
matter: only feelings matter.
If they could make me stop loving you— —that would be the real betrayal.'
She thought it over.
'They can't do that,' she said finally. 'It's the one thing they can't do.
They can make you say anything— anything— —but they can't make you believe it.
They can't get inside you.'
'No,' he said a little more hopefully, 'no; that's quite true.
They can't get inside you.
If you can feel that staying human is worthwhile even when it can't have any
result whatever, you've beaten them.'
He thought of the telescreen with its never sleeping ear.
They could spy upon unite and day, but if you kept your head you could still outwit them.
With all their cleverness they had never mastered the secret of finding out what
another human being was thinking. Perhaps that was less true when you were
actually in their hands.
One did not know what happened inside the Ministry of Love, but it was possible to guess:
tortures, drugs, delicate instruments that registered your nervous reactions,
gradual wearing down by sleeplessness and solitude and persistent questioning.
Facts, at any rate, could not be kept hidden there could be tracks done by inquiry
they could be squeezed out of you by torture.
But if the object was not to stay alive but to stay human, what difference did it
ultimately make?
They could not alter your feelings: for that matter you could not alter them
yourself, even if you wanted to.
They could lay bare in the utmost detail everything that you had done or said or thought;
but the inner heart, whose workings were mysterious even to yourself, remained impregnable